Guide to the Joseph L. Blau Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Joseph L. Blau Papers
1912-1987.
Blau, Joseph L. (Joseph Leon), 1909-1986.
15 linear ft. (ca.12,000 items in 36 boxes).
Columbia University, Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, 535 West 114th St., New York, NY 10027.
4079527
Columbia, A.B., 1931; M.A., 1933; Ph.D., 1944. Professor of religion and philosophy at Columbia University. Member of Fraternity of Leaders of the American Ethical Union; author and scholar in field of American philosophical and religious thought. The collection includes correspondence, manuscripts, course materials, research notes, minutes, clippings, reprints of articles, as well as 25 inscribed or annotated books.
Biographical Note
Born in Brooklyn, New York on May 6, 1909, Dr. Blau received his elementary and high school education in the public schools of New York and New Jersey before entering Columbia. He was awarded his B.A. in 1931. Upon graduation he began teaching in New York's public schools; two years later he completed a thesis on John Biddle, the founder of English Unitarianism, and received an M.A. in English Literature from Columbia. In 1934 he was awarded a fellowship for work toward the Ph.D in Columbia's Philosophy Department. During the following years, Dr. Blau worked as an assistant to Prof. Herbert W. Schneider before completing and publishing his dissertation, The Christian Interpretation of the Cabala in the Renaissance in 1944.
In 1944 Dr. Blau joined Columbia's philosophy department. In succeeding years, he taught courses in American intellectual history and the philosophy of religion. In 1962 after teaching for nearly twenty years in the Philosophy Department, he became a member of the Department of Religion. He served as chairman of this newly-created department from 1965 to 1968 and as director of graduate studies in religion from 1962 to 1974.. During these years Dr. Blau taught undergraduate and graduate courses and seminars and directed dissertations on a wide variety of subjects. He retired from active teaching in June 1977.
During his years at Columbia Dr. Blau authored and edited several books in philosophy and religion including Social Theories of Jacksonian Democracy (1947); Cornerstones of Religious Freedom in America (1949; revised and enlarged ed., 1965); The Story of Jewish Philosophy (1962); and Modern Varieties of Judaism (1966). He is perhaps best known for his work Men and Movements in American Philosophy (1952) which was translated into six languages and became a standard textbook in universities throughout the world. In addition he wrote hundreds of essays, articles and book reviews for both popular and scholarly journals.
While a member of Columbia's.faculty, Dr. Blau was associated with many professional learned organizations including the American Council of Learned Societies, the American Philosophic Association, the American Ethical Union and the American Jewish Historical Society. In addition he held several research fellowships and grants from both the University and outside institutions.
On December 28, 1986 Dr. Blau died at his home in the Riverdale section of the Bronx.
For further biographical information as well as a bibliography of Dr. Blau's writings, one may consult History, Religion, and Spiritual Democracy; Essays in Honor of Joseph L. Blau edited by Maurice Wohlgelernter (New York: Columbia University Press, 1980).
Scope and Content
The collection includes correspondence, manuscripts, course materials, research notes, minutes, clippings, reprints of articles, as well as 25 inscribed or annotated books. The cataloged correspondence includes letters from Alfred Kazin, Reinhold Niebuhr, and Alfred Knopf. The collection offers a comprehensive view of Dr. Blau's professional and intellectual interests during his 50 years of association with Columbia University, as well as an indication of his varied professional involvement with the American Council for Learned Societies, American Society for the study of Religion, Association for Jewish Studies, and the Society for Ethical Culture/American Ethical Union.
The papers of Joseph Leon Blau record almost sixty years of his association with the University, spanning the years from 1929 when he was an undergraduate at the College until 1986, the year of his death, nine years after his formal retirement from teaching. The bulk of this material falls into the years after Dr. Blau joined the faculty in 1944. Specifically, the collection documents Dr. Blau's scholarly interests throughout the 1950s and 1960s most extensively.
The collection consists both of Dr. Blau's office files in the religion department and personal files from his home. It includes much that pertains to his tenure as a member of the religion and philosophy departments, as well as material from his years as a student and from his associations with professional societies unaffiliated with Columbia.
The collection includes correspondence, minutes, clippings, research notes, course materials and manuscripts, typescripts, and reprints of articles, essays and books. It is divided into nine series, namely: Cataloged Correspondence; Arranged Correspondence; Writings; Course Materials; Research Materials; Columbia Activities; Professional Activities; Publicity; and Printed Materials (as well as a folder of miscellaneous items). Descriptions of the contents of these series appear below.
The collection offers a wealth of information to researchers in the fields of philosophy and religion. Its greatest strength is the amount and diversity of Blau's writings which it contains. Most of these writings are gathered together in the Writings Series, although Blau's mastery of the written word is also evident in the Correspondence Series--in particular, in his correspondence with former teachers such as Salo Baron and Herbert Schneider and with colleagues. The writings in this collection document Blau's thoughts on subjects both arcane and popular and enable one to track his development from the young man with a taste for poetry to the distinguished scholar of American philosophy and Judaism. Specifically, the manuscripts in various stages of revision reveal Blau thinking through new ideas, making unexpected connections, testing the borders between disciplines and, always and enthusiastically, beginning new projects. Above all the collection reveals that Blau's mind was encyclopedic, that he defined philosophy and religion broadly and then sought to become an expert on both.
What this collection is less able to suggest is the Blau who again and again declared his love for teaching and who lectured on religion and philosophy to Columbia students from 1944 until 1977. Although the collection contains numerous syllabi and exams, few lecture materials, particularly for the classes he taught in his later years, survive. In addition, although the collection reveals that Dr. Blau served on committees which were instrumental in the establishment of the Religion Department at Columbia, it offers little information documenting his role in this effort.
Finally, researchers should note that this collection is primarily a Columbia collection, that is, it mostly reflects Blau's experiences at the University and, consequently, neglects much that Blau-- as a man committed to taking an active role in his community-- didn't neglect.
The 1990 Addition includes correspondence with publishers, colleagues, friends, and family; articles, drafts of book manuscripts, addresses, and talks; Columbia course files, research files, and printed materials; and personal files of Blau and of his father Rabbi Joel Blau, 1912-1987. Among the cataloged correspondence added are 15 letters from Salo Baron and l letter from Albert Einstein to David Rothstein.
Arrangement
Box 1-2: Cataloged and arranged correspondence; Boxes 3-14: Blau's writings; Boxes 15-17: Course materials; Boxes 18-22: Research materials; Boxes 23-24: Columbia activities; Boxes 25-26: Professional activities; Box 26: Miscellaneous; Boxes 27-29: Publicity; Boxes 30-36: Printed materials.
Subjects
Americal Council for Learned Societies.; American Ethical Union.--Fraternity of Leaders.; American Society for the Study of Religion.; Association for Jewish Studies.; Columbia University--Faculty.; Baron, Salo Wittmayer, 1895-1989.; Blanshard, Paul, 1892-1980.; Boorstin, Daniel J. (Daniel Joseph), 1914-2004.; Buck, Pearl S. (Pearl Sydenstricker), 1892-1973.; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955.; Kazin, Alfred, 1915-1998.; Knopf, Alfred A., 1892-1984.; Niebuhr, Reinhold, 1892-1971.; Rothstein, David, 1942-; Academies and learned societies.; Ethical culture movement.; Judaism--History.; Judaism and philosophy.; Learned institutions and societies.; Philosophy.; Philosophy, Jewish.; Reform Judaism.; Religion.; Religion--Philosophy.; Addresses.; Announcements.; Articles.; Drafts (literary).; Essays.; Examinations.; Fiction.; Financial documents and records.; Lectures.; Lists.; Manuscripts (literary).; Memoranda.; Minutes.; Notes.; Outlines.; Poems.; Programs.; Reports.; Reviews.; Scrapbooks.; Scripts.; Syllabi.; Theses.; Authors.; College teachers.; Consultants.; Editors.; Philosophers.; Scholars.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
The following boxes are located off-site: 2-36. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
10/23/89 M-89-10-23 Blau, Mrs. Eleanor Gift
03/19/90 M-90-03-19 Papers Blau, Elinor Gift
Gift of Mrs Eleanor Blau, 1989 & 1990.
Selected Related Material-- Other Repositories
Additional papers held at: Archives of the Ethical Culture Movement. New York Society for Ethical Culture, New York, NY.
Finding aid available in repository and online.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  Letters to Blau from Pearl S. Buck, Alfred Kazin, Reinhold Niebuhr, Alfred Knopf, Daniel Boorstin, Paul Blanshard, and Salo Baron. Also, letter from Albert Einstein to David Rosenstein.
  - (Box 1)
- Series II: Arranged Correspondence
  - Subseries II.1: General Correspondence, 1932-1986
    Series is almost evenly divided between letters received and carbons of letters sent. It includes all correspondence except that which is included in the Letters from Publishers, Permissions to Print or ACLS series (and some letters filed with specific essays or addresses).
    Among the correspondents are Algernon Black, Arthur Hyman, Elizabeth Janeway, Elaine Pagels, Paul Pfeutze and Herbert Schneider.
    Incoming and outgoing letters are arranged separately. Incoming letters are filed alphabetically; letters from unidentified correspondents are filed at the end of this sequence. Outgoing letters are filed chronologically by year; undated letters are filed at the end of this sequence.
    - (Box 1)
  - Subseries II.2: Correspondence with Publishers, 1946-1986
    Series consists of letters to Blau from book and periodical publishers as well as royalty statements from Prentice-Hall, Inc. relating to Men and Movements in American Philosophy. Also included are reader's reports of various authors' works submitted by Blau at the request of publishers, and a number of book contracts between Blau and various publishers.
    various publishers. The letters cover the years 1946-1986. Many of them are invitations to submit journal articles and book reviews or reminders from editors that publishing deadlines are near. The royalty statements were issued at six-month periods and cover the years 1952-1972. The reader's reports cover the years 1980-1981.
    Letters are arranged chronologically; royalty statements, contracts, and reader's reports are filed separately and arranged chronologically.
    - (Box 2)
  - Subseries II.3: Permissions to Print, 1951, 1962-1963
    Series consists of letters from Blau and Salo Baron requesting permission to quote from manuscript materials in Men and Movements in American Philosphy and Jews of the United States: A Documentary History as well as letters from institutions and individuals in response to these requests.
    Most of the letters are perfunctory; however some document the difficulties Blau and Baron encountered in obtaining permission to quote from personal papers in Jews of the United States.
    Letters for the two books are filed separately. Within this arrangement, request and permission letters are kept together and filed alphabetically under the name of the individual or institution granting permission.
    - (Box 2)
- Series III: Writings
  - Subseries III.1: Book Drafts, circa 1947-1973, undated
    Annotated typescripts and handwritten drafts of chapters, parts of chapters and outlines of chapters of books edited or authored by Blau including Social Theories of Jacksonian Democracy (1947), Men and Movements in American Philosophy (1952), Judaism: Postbiblical and Talmudic Periods (1954), William James: Pragmatism and Other Essays (1963) Francis Wayland: The Elements of Moral Science (1963), Cornerstones of Religious Freedom (rev. ed, 1964), and Reform Judaism: A Historical Perspective (1973). More than half of these drafts have not been identified.
    Arranged alphabetically by title of book when draft is identifiable; unidentified manuscripts are filed at the end of the alphabetical sequence.
    - (Box 3-5)
  - Subseries III.2: Articles and Essays, circa 1931-1986
    Typescripts and, less often, manuscripts of Blau's shorter writings. Undated pieces were probably written in the 1950s and 1960s. Representative subjects of these essays are Jewish history and philosophy, John Dewey, David Hume, the history of American philosophy and the philosophy of religion. Several biographies of American thinkers are also included. Most were published in journals such as the Journal of Philosophy, the Humanist and Jewish Social Studies.
    Arranged alphabetically by title of article or essay.
    - (Box 6-10)
  - Subseries III.3: Book Reviews, circa 1939-1976
    Mostly unmarked typescripts of one or two-page reviews and review notes written by Blau for publication in scholarly journals. Reviews are primarily of books in philosophy and religion such as Martin Buber's Tales of the Hasidim and Leonard White's The Federalists.
    Arranged alphabetically by title of reviewed book.
    - (Box 10)
  - Subseries III.4: Unpublished Manuscripts, undated
    These boxes contain almost entire book drafts as well as a number of shorter articles that are suitable for publication. As such, these files are not to be used in any way without the permission of Mrs. Joseph Blau or her heirs.
    - (Box 11-12)
  - Subseries III.5: Encyclopedia Articles, circa 1964
    Reprints and original typescipts of short articles by Blau including a variety of biographies and topics in philosophy. These articles were published in the Encyclopedia of Philosophy, the Encyclopedia of Religion, and an encyclopedia published by the Arete Company. Also included are a group of encyclopedia articles whose eventual destination is unknown.
    Arranged alphabetically by title of article.
    - (Box 13)
  - Subseries III.6: Fiction and Literary Criticism, circa 1929-1931
    Typescripts and manuscripts of Blau's short stories (such as "Time and Chance; or How I Murdered My Great-Aunt") and literary criticism (such as "A Critical Study of the Elizabethan Sonnet Sequence") Most of these works were written for undergraduate and graduate English classes; some include instructor's comments.
    Unarranged.
    - (Box 13)
  - Subseries III.7: Poems, circa 1930 and 1943
    Typescripts, carbons and clippings from Columbia magazines and newspapers of short poems by Blau. Also includes a 1943 NY Times Magazine clipping of Blau's poem "A Fantasy" with a typed draft.
    - (Box 13)
  - Subseries III.8: Addresses/Talks, circa 1949-1985, undated
    Typescripts, manuscripts and photocopies of addresses--other than classroom lectures--delivered by Blau on a multitude of topics (similar to those of his essays). Most of these addresses were given at New York area ethical unions, and at universities across the country. Included is a series of lectures Blau delivered to the 92nd St. YW-YMHA. Also included are several tributes Blau gave to colleagues and friends (Salo Baron, for example).
    Arranged alphabetically by title; untitled addresses are filed after this alphabetical sequence.
    - (Box 13-14)
- Series IV: Course Materials
  - Subseries IV.1: Columbia University, circa 1946-1976, undated
    Photocopies of syllabi, reading lists, handouts, and exams as well as typed and handwritten lecture notes for graduate and undergraduate courses and seminars taught at Columbia. Also included are outlines of planned courses Blau was to give.
    Approximately 35 philosophy and 19 religion courses are represented, although for most courses only photocopies of syllabi and exams are included. Those courses with substantial lecture notes are Greek Philosophy, American Social Philosophy, History and Literature of American Philosophy, Philosophy of John Dewey and History of Judaism. Most philosophy course materials appear to be from the 1950s; most religion course materials appear to be from the 1960s.
    Philosophy and Religion courses are arranged separately; when known, course name and number are indicated on folders. Materials are filed in course number order; those for which course number is unknown are filed after the numerical sequence. One folder of miscellaneous materials for which both course name and number are unknown is filed after both the religion and philosophy course materials. One folder of miscellaneous materials for philosophy courses taught at Barnard are filed after other philosophy course materials.
    - (Box 15-16)
  - Subseries IV.2: Other Universities, 1948-1951, 1961-1962
    Photocopies of syllabi and reading lists as well as handwritten lecture notes for philosophy and religion courses taught by Blau at The New School for Social Research, Baruch College, Vassar College, the University of Minnesota and the University of Arkansas. Also included is a typewritten outline of a course Blau proposed to teach at the John L. Elliot Institute in 1949.
    Arranged in alphabetical order by name of institution.
    - (Box 16)
  - Subseries IV.3: Class Notes, circa 1929-1934
    Both typed and handwritten notes on loose sheets and index cards for philosophy and history courses Blau took as an undergraduate and graduate student at Columbia. Includes what appear to be typewritten lecture notes of Salo Baron's 1929 Survey of Jewish History course and of Herbert Schneider's philosophy department course, "Study of Religions." Also includes photocopies of miscellaneous syllabi and of an an incomplete 80-page outline of Eastern religions with some handwritten comments. Series also contains undergraduate papers and Blau's master's thesis on John Biddle, along with what appear to be Blau's father's notes at Columbia.
    The history and philosophy course materials are arranged separately. Blau's notes for Baron's Jewish History course are filed with other history class notes; his notes for Schneider's religion course are filed with other philosophy class notes. Within that arrangement, papers and cards are filed in rough chronological order; the papers, other notes, miscellaneous photocopies, and undated materials are filed at the end.
    - (Box 17)
  - Subseries IV.4: Reports on High School Teaching, circa 1938-1940
    Typescripts and carbon copies of reports written by Blau while a teacher of English and speech in New York public high schools. Titles of reports include "Classroom Use of Auditory Aids" and "The Function of Drills in the Teaching of Speech."
    Arranged in alphabetical order by title of report.
    - (Box 17)
- Series V: Research Materials, circa 1944-1986, undated
  Miscellaneous materials on a wide range of topics. This series consists of many articles and assorted writings by other authors that Blau was using in his research. Also included are many incomplete manuscripts and typescripts of Blau's, as well as some translations. Most materials are undated.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject; a folder of miscellaneous materials follows the alphabetical sequence. Subjects which appear in quotation marks on folders are Blau's; untitled folders have been assigned subject headings on the basis of their apparent content. Individual folders contain index cards, scraps of paper, "blue books" and loose sheets arranged in little discernible order.
  - (Box 18-22)
- Series VI: Columbia Activities
  - Subseries VI.1: Committee on Admissions to Columbia College, 1954-1960
    Photocopies and typescripts of Committee minutes, reports and memoranda regarding meeting schedules, nominations of faculty interviewers, applicant statistics and brief statements of admissions policies.
    Arranged chronologically by year.
    - (Box 23)
  - Subseries VI.2: Committee on Facilities, 1961-1962
    Photocopies and carbon copies of memoranda and reports received by Blau who, as a departmental representative, was involved with the renovations and reallocation of space in Hamilton Hall.
    Arranged chronologically.
    - (Box 23)
  - Subseries VI.3: Council for Research in the Social Sciences, 1960-1964
    Photocopies and some typescripts of minutes of Council meetings which Blau attended as a member of the Executive Committee. Also includes a photocopy of the 1960 Annual Report and a list of publications sponsored by the Council.
    - (Box 23)
  - Subseries VI.4: Philosophy Department Minutes, Memoranda, etc., 1949-1960
    Photocopies of memos to department faculty members detailing upcoming department lectures and events as well as minutes of department meetings at which course offerings and faculty appointments are discussed. Also includes minutes of the 1959 and 1960 meetings of the Committee on Instruction as well as Blau's roll book for 1949-1955.
    - (Box 23)
  - Subseries VI.5: Religion Department Minutes, Memoranda, etc., 1961-1979
    Photocopies and typescripts of minutes of meetings of the Department (beginning in 1962), and its predecessor, the interdepartmental Committee on Religious Studies. Series also contains some photocopies of minutes for the Joint Committee for the Ph.D in Religion as well as typescripts of proposed courses and of reading lists for religion majors.
    Coverage of the irregularly scheduled department and committee meetings is sporadic: the years 1961 through 1963 are the most extensively represented; there are very few items relating to later years.
    Minutes and memoranda for the Committees and the Departments are arranged separately arranged separately from the miscellaneous materials. Within that classification, materials are arranged chronologically by year; undated materials are filed at the end of chronological sequences.
    - (Box 23)
  - Subseries VI.6: Stokes Prize Committee, 1951-1952
    Memos and notes to and from Blau regarding the topic for an essay on the basis of which this academic prize is awarded.
    - (Box 23)
  - Subseries VI.7: University Seminar on American Civilization, 1954-1961
    Photocopies of minutes of monthly seminars sponsored by Columbia and attended by Blau and other scholars interested in American studies. Also includes a photocopied directory of members and list of papers read.
    Minutes are lengthy and incorporate papers presented at the seminar as well as ensuing discussions.
    Only minutes of meetings 1-9, 11-19, 21, 23, 26, 28-32, 34-42, 44 and 46 are included.
    Arranged in meeting number order.
    - (Box 24)
  - Subseries VI.8: Other University Seminars, 1970-1980
    Material relating to two other university seminars: On Irael and Jewish Studies, and On Studies in Religion.
    - (Box 24)